so following on from the discussion on
long conflict this topic of non conflict
I was read the verse of two verses from
the Dhammapada chapter 10 the violence
or it's translated as the stick speak
not maliciously to anyone for those thus
spoken to might retort okay
first point might retaliate it is a very
odd indeed malicious speech is dukkha
and retaliate retaliation may be the
results what is malicious speech is it the
what is malicious speech is it the
choice of words is it the intonation is
it shouting at you or not what
determines malicious features malicious
pitch your attention exactly what
attention intention to harm so that's
the first point here because many people
are caught up in the idea that speech in
itself these malicious like the words of
a chosen means immediately means this is
the motivation but with what same words
the same for any type of action action
is determined as good or bad and
wholesome and wholesome militias or non
malicious by the intention behind it not
by the content of it certain type of
action is always unwholesome such as
killing sexual intercourse and so on in terms of
sexual intercourse and so on in terms of
the precepts lying stealing that's
abandoned that not to be done as the
Buddha said but every other action
that's not covered by that is then
basically determined by your intention
and speech especially so that's
important thing again to realize the
motivation behind the action is what
determines it not like I will never use
these words I will never raise my voice
because I must not be malicious that
means you have a view that maliciousness
is there where it isn't and because of
that you're not seeing it for what it
actually is and it's gonna continue you
maintain me exact
so you can have your perfect you know
psychotherapy type of speech to never
say anything conflicting to anyone and
hate their guts fully be rooted a new
wheel but have this perfect tone soft
words spoken to them love this money
I'll be smile on your face exactly and
there is that there is that suit away
the Buddha said that said some
companions in the Holy life a softly
spoken agreeable and loved by everybody
but they have from views they don't
understand what the root of the problem
is they don't understand the way out of
it they don't send anything but they
please into everybody and they're
extremely blameworthy
oh it's because the view makes them
blame body then you have the other type
of people who are actually upsetting to
others they don't have agreeable speech
to them to others but they also have the
right view and they know where the
problem is and they can basically teach
that and so on and then look they're not
blank word because they cannot have a
malicious intent because they understood
it so it doesn't matter how you speak
its reach is not malicious by itself
exactly it's why you saying it and
what's your intention behind and again
that's a sometimes I don't know how
often but but I've seen a number of
times that people it will refuse to even
accept this which is very clear and all
you need to do is read more suitors and
you'll see it said many times but people
still refuse to accept that because well
if you accept that the motivation
determines whether your speech is good
or bad whether your action is good or
bad that means then you become more
aware of your motivation and on your
responsibility there are two things as
opposed to just blindly adhere to not
raising your course not saying certain
words always speaking with certain
facial expression and that's your
practice that's palpable that's doable
that's observable and that's why it's
nothing to do with understanding and go
see it means that it's also presents a
tool it's very presentable yeah it's
very relate others look plays are very
relatable externally a good report has
please it's fine it's a natural thing to
assume that but again you have to ask
yourself okay but am I
to know that what the way out of
suffering is and how this contributes it
or not if the answer is no you mustn't
take for granted any assumption that you
have and the first time I read that suta
were what that monk was basically really
rude pull these people and other monks
talking down to them and calling them
names and whatnot and people got upset
and went to the Buddha I mean obviously
must have been a big deal because many
people went to the Buddha for that sick
it wasn't just one person complained the
Buddha called him and then oh so that he
was another hunt and he do tell me but
you should still police your speech and
change your habits no he said no he's
another blameless
he is blameless doesn't matter how he
speaks and then he said the reason he
still speaks like that because his
previous lives and so on and so forth
and at the time when I read that it
wouldn't make sense all about it because
in my mind the idea of in our hunt is
justice always and you cannot send as it
will wait a minute if something is
upsetting to somebody it doesn't mean
that it's wrong or not even unwholesome
is the intention of the person who does
it that's what determines it but then
you realize oh so then I should start
looking in my own intentionality be
behind my own seemingly justifiable
actions and choices are making and that
already makes you doubtful fills you
with anxiety because you realize you can
tomorrow decide to do the otherwise you
can just walk away
you are not justified to do anything
unless you choose to do it and you
realize do you get your only
justification did I choose that I've
chosen that's it and that's not the
justification that's felt much more
responsibly much more heavily much more
unpleasantly so it's better then for me
to ignore
maybe the suitors they talk about that
and then just focus and blind you adhere
to certain types of behavior certain
type of speech certain type of soft
voice certain type of this certain type
of that like if you naturally do that to
speak like that that's absolutely fine
but if you're doing it so basically you
think that's where the practice is which
then allows you to not look at the
motivation why are you doing it that's
why it's not father you might be doing
it a right motivation but you must
realize that speaking harshly
role probably result in retaliation from
the yeah of course exactly you have it yeah
yeah of course exactly you have it yeah
respect you it's politics it's part of
the deal exactly you cannot pretend or
say like that monk and the monk did not
complain about people complaining about
him I'm sure him being in our hunt he
I'm sure him being in our hunt he
understood that well it's part of the
package if he were to by any chance
decide to deal with all these complaints
he would have maybe changed his speech
but he would have had a practical reason
for it he would have not changed it out
of some misguided view that softly
speaking means the Dhamma not raising
your voice means the Dhamma because it
doesn't and all you need to do is read
the Vinaya suitors and see how the
Buddha spoke to the monks that broke the
rules I remember there was another thing
I was quite shocked when I saw the first
time because in your mind the Buddha is
this mix of you know Mahayana and
everything else this loving-kindness you
know Joey always on his face and then I
came across the winner suitors when the
month done things they shouldn't have
and then the Buddha came and rebuked
them and the world she used to them you
like well if you don't know that where
the speech is full of ill-will is
determined by the motivation behind the
speech not the content of the speech you
will think the Buddha was furious I mean
I don't want to repeat stuff he said
because he was quite irate like it
stupid you fool why he was boys in that
when it came to those sexual rules that
monks broke the words he used in
comparisons he made it was like shocking
at the time but then it was well
actually there was the appropriate a
proportional response to the action they
committed if he was a bit so fine
brother next time you'll do better then
a good ass take it seriously exactly so
the whole order will decline as a result
of it so he was that level of you know
harshness means that's how much he was
required but you to judge that that he
was full of evil because of the words
he's used what means your own ideas of
it the quarter is guided what the
problem is
so in terms of you know having that
perspective that there is going to be
some sort of retaliation hmm that's a
relationship means that there's going to
be some sort of it's chemically all
relationships will be conflicted
conflicting exact conflicting well I
think that's every relationship or that
is to some degree there's always a
conflict when two beings come together
conflict in a sense means you know
they're already different in some regard
it's but if if say if both of the people
beings were to protect their mindset of
non conflict no Neil will it cannot be
any conflict arising doesn't matter what
words they use if you're unable to get
full of your will towards me even if I'm
full available toward you that means
already there is no room for a will to
arise in our relationships
because it needs to be reciprocated
needs to be given back but now imagine
if both of us are incapable of ill-will
towards each other no because I love you
so much and you dig a friend of mine
because no I protect my mind if no neo
builds so much that I don't care who is
in front of me I will not allow my mind
to hate them and if you do the same that
is the divine abode incapable of hatred
on both sides both parties regardless of
what said what's done what do you see
yes Julia hunger is there doesn't mean I
will be oblivious to your behavior
because I'm so full of non your will
that you can do anything no as to the
recognize that was a foolish thing to do
and now I can tell you because it won't
be rooted in my hatred of you Nouriel
well and furthermore you'll be able to
hear it and not lose your composure
because you will not have your will
towards me so it doesn't matter how
blunt things can get you will not lose
the context not neither party will lose
the context but it but the party
person who has that non-conflicting
mindset right intentions hmm who's
coming from the right place if he says
well you're a fool but he must also
realize it that person is come from will
be able to hear it or not
hmm because usually people not gonna be
able to hear this because they older
they don't have that context to begin
with yeah and they will never have that
context to begin with if they don't
start looking for it in the right place
which is your own mindset in regard to
how you're feeling here regardless of
what you heard seen taste tongues and
some of the wise person knows when to
say knows exactly what is the right time to
knows exactly what is the right time to
say well it's not gonna be beneficial
exactly exact why because they already
have that greater perspective of
non-conflict Gnomeo will non-resistance
too so in other words if you don't
resist to how you're feeling you're not
gonna become impatient to say something
because the reason people become
impatient and say things right things
but at the wrong time is because they
can't bear how they're feeling at the
time so they must say it quickly but if
your priorities don't resist how you
feel regardless of what it is you cannot
even give into that which means whenever
you say it it would be the right time
because you're not saying it out of
impatience which is a form of resisting
to how you're feeling at a time
impatient and you also will not be
bothered by the thought what if I never
say this what if this person never hears
that you didn't differently it's not
your problem that's what your dance is
and then you know you can say it because
you won't be rooted in any form of
resistance or impatience that you might
have because yes literally what if I
were to die after the next in-breath how
important would it be to me to say this
she realize the only reason why things
are important pressing I must say you
cannot resist compulsive is because you
resist are you feeling you want to
quickly deal with that
patient means you forsake the framework
for the sake of dealing with the content
and the next verse following who is that
was he the broken gum yeah this is
that's that's what I'm saying basically
yeah when even if I'm fully oh of your
will and your mind is incapable of will
blow because it's not reciprocated back
to me there is no ill-will in the
relation that's like the gong is broken
doesn't matter how much I'm hitting it
there will be no sound resonate
interview because it needs the response
yeah now imagine if both sides are
broken that the stick your head in the
gong is broken there is no um no
resonance of annual will impossible to
occur yeah that's that conflict it's
coming from one can only go so far yeah
and then still down upon hatred breeds
hate yes I wanted me needy cannot occur
otherwise and there is going to be
hatred it is going to be can you have
can you hatred without resistance to
what you hate is there any form of
hatred other dinner resistant humbly
amplifies resistance there isn't so if
you're incapable resistance to us how
you feeling
would you be able of hating anything
based on your feeling impossible so
instead of trying to deal with your
hatred chase it just stop resisting how
you feel in regard to anything and
everyone it'll be capable hatred you
know in the world there will always be
those night that's where the world is so
then what do you expect you expect for
you to protect your mind of not hating
amidst everybody hating me but trying to
make others not hate and going out of
your way to make others not there will
be able to change you is this thing how
you feel on account of experience you
hate so are you missing the point you'll
make yourself liable to yourself hating
them cuz your pen you said things about
four majors it'll never be completed
impossible to concerts
detection yeah we're The Grates filter
give me the opposite of the peaceful
mind peaceful life into the promisee -
is that exactly the opposite yep trying
to make a difference yeah that's a test
and you will know that if you look where
your motivation is rooted even
motivation like why am i practicing in
such and such manner what for is it to
manage what I don't want to accept on
the level of my feeling is it to develop
indifference towards my feelings is it
this is adapt and if your practice is
about you know dealing with hate dealing
with this spreading love you realize
well that's quite a limited application
already it's dependent on these things
which means you cannot possibly prevent
people from acting foolishly saying
things that will be upsetting it's even
possible so then the only reason you
will be trying to prevent that is
because you still hold the view that
they will basically save you from the
discomfort and as such you remain liable
to the same discomfort so that that
first can all read if like a broken gun
you silenced yourself you have
approached the burner for malice or
contention is no longer found in you yes
what do malice contention hatred you
will have in common can you resist
something if that thing is not felt
impossible
so then if you stop resisting to how you
feel you then stop cultivating men's
hatred contentions everything else
impossible to engage with those things
yes sliders yeah that's the true sign
for the Lotus not lately you know you
saw in your mouth shut yes no noble
science don't know science you